[Music]
she turns she
you need
and
the Sun yes and
the dog
-
[Music]
I'm good
we turns her cage
time to answer a ten year
[Music]
- son Gator now togheter now turn to do
counsel to the attorney
no pension and so gay John
turn to
[Music]
Sergey engineer
he does
[Music]
all right then so welcome to the wisdom
of our new gardener which is a new
course new ACI course and I'd like to
tell you a little bit about the course
and the plan and then we'll get into it
so I've been we've been doing first
there was two retreats a year in Arizona
to teach the lamrim the steps of the
path by Pavano in between which my
teacher taught me several times and over
25 years period and I thought I would
like to pass it on word by word you know
in my lifetime and we're making good
progress on that I think it's been eight
or nine years and it's going a little
slower than we expected but that's
because we're going deeper and deeper
and I really love it
and I'm committed to that and we will
finish it so I think three more years
four more years and I don't know that
retreats were increased we added a
retreat in Guadalajara and we added a
retreat in Thailand and so it went from
two retreats a year to four retreats a
year and a couple of things happened I
think it became too many for people to
come to I think it's you know even if
you're like very wealthy person to fly
to Thailand and then fly to Guadalajara
and fly to Arizona it's expensive so I I
thought I was trying to think of how to
solve this problem so I I thought we
would kind of change the this between
the the fall retreated Diamond Mountain
we started doing common-law Sheila
explanation of the diamond cutter and I
guess it took three or four years and we
finished it and we did it during the
long rim so people came for seven or
eight or ten days for lung room and then
people stayed for the gardener if they
wanted to go sorry Carla Sheila if they
wanted to go deeper and it's too long
like you're gonna get divorced if if you
stay here for two weeks and your
husband's like what are you doing and
starts trying to solve all these
problems and I had an idea that in the
fall in the autumn which means this
month October in Diamond Mountain we
could just do the gardening and then in
Guadalajara
if you guys want and if you will we have
to do some organization work there which
we'll talk about this week but we could
continue with the long room there with
male I got male with some extra sauce
got male from Mexico City I'm so happy
so you know not just la Maryam which is
boring and technical and so we spice it
my ideas to spice it with other
nagarjuna space so the garden had taught
many things and I would like to add some
poblanos and jalapenos in the garden of
jalapeno to Chile to the Mexico program
and then same in Thailand but this time
we're kind of trying to make Thailand
more of a family which we encourage
people to bring their parents which is
sort of more common in Asia
and to bring their children and have
special programs for them in Thailand so
so Thailand's kind of taken care of we
have lots of additional things there and
then diamond mountain in the springtime
we'll just do long rim which people
think is dry and hard it's it's been
eight or nine years and they're like
just long when's this gonna end
first thing I don't want it to end and I
think it's very important so I'm gonna
keep going even if there's one person
here called geshe-la
keep going okay so I'm not gonna stop at
the Long Room I think it's very
important and I want to pass on what was
given to me so that's the plan but this
time and then I'm thinking maybe Tim we
organized some this just came in my head
some podcast or something in between the
whole year about the guard you know
because you can't do the Guardian on
once a year you need a little
reinforcement so we'll figure out it I
did an interesting podcast to Germany in
write a couple days ago and it was very
well people really enjoyed it and many
many people watched it so maybe we try
some more that to keep you up on the
guard you know so you don't just do the
gardener once a year okay so let's try
something like that from my bathroom in
my house just the upper part
and we'll do that so I also got a lot of
feedback that geshe-la in the lamrim
course there's not much chance for the
students to interact and to participate
you know you are just talking for 10
hours every day and this is how I was
trained
you know in the monastery you go to
class sometimes 8 hours sometimes 10
hours you you just sit there and they
talk to you you know and they teach you
and you actually you're not allowed to
ask questions and you're not allowed to
say anything almost you're not allowed
to PB either and so I was brought up
that way for 25 years you know I did
that for 25 years so it's in my blood
too I want revenge I want to make the
students sit for eight hours and no no
to anything and try to look awake learn
how to sleep with your eyes open but
I've been watching what Scott and Ari
have done such a good job at the college
and our College in Sedona and I'm very
impressed mostly it's a reach idea
because she did an education degree
there's a lot of interaction the
students have to do a lot of work the
students get a lot of chances to
interact they get a lot of chances to
design things they do videos they do
lots of cool things they do game show
they have buzzers and questions and they
get they win coffee-shop certificates
and it's a lot of fun so I'm kind of
like many of us I'm jealous of this
program
and I'm thinking how to steal some of
those things so I'm gonna change the
guard you know a little bit different I
gave a program in China called China
soft power we chose we limit to 40
executives mostly they own their own
companies and we want them to learn the
ancient culture of China and use it in
their business you know so this is
organized by Stanley and elephant
they're doing a really good job it's
amazing yeah and we have a small
translator group there well 40 people
and they are learning to translate one
of the greatest books of China which is
by a master named eunsuh who's a student
of fencing fencing went to India for 17
years walked through India visited
nagarjuna's library 1,300 years ago and
his student wrote one of the greatest
books on interpreting the Buddha the art
of interpretation and it's 2,000 pages
and it's sorry fourteen hundred and
seventy-five pages and gets lost trying
not to exaggerate
he got information from his partner
about this so anyway we're gonna work
through this book it's a great
explanation of what the Buddha really
meant and so I was thinking how to do
both at the same time you know I have to
go there and I have to wake up at 6
o'clock and and teach in the morning the
translators and then in the afternoon I
have to teach the business executives so
we made a new system
inch engine which i think is very
exciting the executives come to the
translation class big big people some of
them have very large companies one of
the people who came before is in charge
of 1.5 million people and you know I
have to I had this idea that the
business executives have to come to the
translation class and then they have to
choose the cool ideas we call diamond
mining cultural mining they have to mine
the translators class for cool ideas to
use in their business okay and this is
what geshe-la does this is why you need
gets learn but I'm gonna teach you what
I do then you don't need me anymore I
take those classic books important books
I studied them and I go mining I take
out the diamonds and I make DCI programs
you see that's what I do so I'm telling
you my secret then I thought let's let
the business executives they're smart
people there are big people let them go
mining let them go through the great
books and let them pick out great ideas
and say oh this would be useful in my
business if you change this to modern
life disappear coal in my business you
know
oh this idea would be cool in my
business I can use this in my business
you see so it was very smart because we
were very stressed out we didn't have
much time
we made the student to write the course
you see and they and we just chided we
tried to experiment then they had groups
they got into groups and each group
discusses their great idea how to use
one of the translation pieces in their
real in their business you see and so
each group came up with their own
application to real life of this ancient
you answer takeout from you enter these
ideas and use in their real life and and
then we had a competition each group
choose two or three of their best ideas
and they have to find a photograph right
edom picture one picture which is
perfect for that idea so if that ideas
about like not yelling at employees then
you have a picture of a boss like that
or something something you can remember
the application the idea and we call it
um right I what is it idea image so they
have to counter the chance of the course
they have to pick out each individual
person pick out oh this idea can use
form for my employees or this idea I can
use for my investors or this idea I can
use for my customers
you see I mean and then they have to
make a picture then they get in their
own groups they pick the best ones and
then the group's compete the group start
to get up and say this is our we have
these top two ideas for real life that
we mind remind from the ancient wisdom
you know and actually that's all I do
that's my whole life you know if I teach
you that I can go to Florida and relax
right with with them less gathers so
anyway so I was thinking me and Tim were
working really hard jingly we were
trying to think about how to make the
garden a more interactive not not all
the Tibetan system where I talk and you
sit and try not to fall asleep
and hold the pp so we have this idea
okay so I'm gonna teach the guard unit
okay I will teach the gardener's
greatest book which we'll talk about
it's called wisdom it's just called
protein young say protein young like the
Russians are closer yeah yeah yes me oh
so we're gonna go through the most
famous book of Buddhism really and and
no one teaches it much and we're gonna
go through the garden of wisdom okay and
I'm gonna explain it to you and then
your job I'm gonna and I made pretty
tough homeworks for you you know not a
CI style little tougher okay
little tough homeworks for you so one of
your jobs while you are being silent and
while your phone is taking a ten-day
vacation okay which will give you all
the important information about with
Naggar janice greatest book but you're
also gonna write an idea okay you're
gonna go mining yourself in your room
everyday one idea one different idea
oh we can use this in business or we can
use this in teaching Dharma or we can
use this in a family problem so your job
every afternoon number one you have to
do your homework to do your homework do
your notebooks active now they need them
this morning they are to take notes
yeah okay hmm okay you'll get a notebook
okay and you have to take notes okay
because there is no reading there is no
reading okay maybe I'll give you wisdom
at the end but it's just from your own
notes and from your homework you're
gonna have to create at least one cool
idea mining for diamonds every day okay
so this is a trick if you're a teacher
I'm teaching you a trick although now
now they're gonna listen more carefully
you should see those business executives
they're like yeah last time they were
like you know now they're like I'm gonna
get my ideas gonna be better than all
gone here and so you gotta take notes
okay if you hear a cool idea write it
down okay and then you'll get a homework
okay and it'll be on your homework so
your homework has three parts number one
there's about I don't know six to ten
questions that you have to answer okay
number two there's a meditation
assignment from the lion stance and it's
just do level one do level to do looking
like done then number three there's a
whole page assignment that says what's
your cool idea from today's teaching
what's your cool diamond mining idea
okay and there's a box at the bottom of
the homework that you're going to get
graded on your idea and it says there's
I think four questions on the homework I
have it right here number one is this an
important idea you know like I don't
want to see I learned
from the gardener that I should have two
cups of coffee every day you know this
is not important okay so first grade you
get is how important is this idea is it
something that everybody needs
number two is it creative okay or did
you copy the first homework answer you
said I mean did you do something cool is
it cool so you got a thing cool okay we
want cool okay we want something fun and
interesting and cool okay number three
is it authoritative is it really in the
gardener or did you make it up okay and
and this is a line that you have to have
as a teacher how much you put of your
own idea and how much is in the gardener
and I want about seventy five percent in
the gardener okay I don't want you to
rewrite the gardener okay you are using
the gardener okay and and if you're
smart you will find a cool like a
diamond inside - last morning teaching
which other people didn't notice that's
the goal you see you'll find some cool
idea that people can use in their life
which which is inside gets less teaching
but the other people next you didn't
hear it they didn't notice it okay and
and be be open to anything I'm open to
anything okay if you say here's a new
way to tie your shoes every morning you
know do it with your left hand it may be
something cool okay son
I like creativity I you know I grew up
in that kind of environment where my
parents encouraged us to be very
creative okay
so creativity important authoritative
and the most important thing the fourth
thing your new idea is going to be
graded on is can
you use it in real life is it something
people can use in their real life okay
so it can't be two New Age okay it has
to be something you can use in a real
life like the two husbands in the
kitchen I use it every day I use it
almost every day
I invented it okay doc that's what I
found in the scripture and I use it
myself every day so we want something
that people can use in their real life
okay now how are your stuff be graded
okay Tim mm we're gonna put you in
groups from the first day so your
homework will say what's your group
number okay and you will have a group
number I think the groups are seven to
ten people I don't know seven to eight
people okay and you will be in a group
you won't meet your group till the end
of the week okay but you will have a
group number like group nothing like we
can say sinem is in group number five
okay and please put that on your
homework there's a space and empty space
where you put your group number okay and
then Tim my suggestion is the homework
greater number one we make a commitment
from the management of HCI
to grade your homework in 24 hours okay
you will get your homework back the next
day okay
not the old ACI system where it goes to
another country and comes back after
seven years okay all right so we commit
and we're going to need some violent
tips creating a special team to grade
the homers why I think that's important
each homework grader will grate a
different team each day okay so if
there's a homework grader who's really
stupid and doesn't understand your great
idea you only meet them once okay your
homework will only meet them once okay
so if the homework grader is not
creative themself don't worry okay you
will get a fair treatment they're equal
abuse from each of the homework
greatness okay so I'd like that system
how my grader has to do different teams
every day okay and we have to rotate
through the kids you're gonna all the
homeworks from group five are going to
go to what grader and then the next day
they go to a different grader okay got
it so it's kind of fair then at the end
of the week we're going to ask you to
choose your to the two we call them real
applications okay so I invented a new
word you ready
called real app okay real out then we're
gonna say it fast real app not relapse
okay real app it means application to
real life okay you really so get loud
now we have items right yeah that's the
picture then we have relapse that's the
idea of how to use the scripture for my
real life okay then we have life tools
but that's DC I talk and I don't want to
mix DC I talk and AC I talk I think they
should have our own languages we
shouldn't mix them too much because
that's for business people there are
some countries where we're not allowed
to teach a CI and we should respect that
and we should be careful then on the
other hand we should have our own
language for for a CI and we'll make it
better than DC I
okay so relapse okay then on your
homework on the last page you're gonna
trade things for your real app okay and
you'll get your homework today for
today's class
if geshe-la ever gets to the class first
thing about a real app you need a good
name you could a good propaganda name
catchy name okay
catchy name like two husbands in the
kitchen the pen or the fourth test okay
don't call it my ideas for real
application in life taken from the
gardener of how to use the Forester okay
make a good short name like you're
marketing your idea to the world okay
like make it a cool name like we call
this course the aid Invisibles this
course we're going to have five negation
of courses we will do five years of
wisdom this book will take five years
okay the first year is called the aid
invisible now aren't you curious about
what's invisible besides your paychecks
so make a cool name like that okay so
your first job give it a cool name
okay from marketing you know iPad iPod
you know recall iPhone you know they
have these names right they made them up
okay so I'd like a cool name okay number
two then describe your cool idea I said
one or two sentences but if you're gas
law you will have 23 commas okay like
describe your cool idea okay if it takes
longer it's okay but the homework
graders are going to have a breakdown so
okay more than two sentences okay but
don't go on the back of the page
and don't write too small okay by the
way if you speak a foreign language
Tim's going to make sure you can write
everything in a foreign language and the
graders will be from different countries
and so don't worry about it you don't
have to write in English or Chinese or
Spanish it's up to you okay what
language is comfortable for you it's
fine
and Tim's going to make sure we have
graders for each of them he oh yeah I'm
up for it
okay good luck this is your job you know
this is your job if you need I'll write
you an idea from the garden how to do it
okay
in last thing you cannot use the
internet but I would like you to write
down what kind of edom would you like
for your idea okay what kind of picture
photograph are you gonna find at the end
of the week for your cool idea okay like
what's the picture that's so cool about
for your item okay and we will give you
access okay Tim to a website I like one
two three ara it's a stock photograph
website they cost about $3 or $5 and
they're very high quality and I use
those I use that website I think they
have beautiful photographs so look we'll
give you that now on the last full day
of retreat or maybe starting the day
before the unmatched area we will you
will meet with your group and you'll be
allowed to talk and you will go through
I think we need two days of meetings Tim
but will working on
you have time to sit with your group and
everybody gets to show their best to
items and their best to ideas and then
your group is going to choose how many
10 I'll just - yeah I think that's all
we have time for your group will choose
2 to represent your group ok up done up
the whole proposals ok and you have to
find the pictures on those days last day
and a half or something ok you have to
find your pictures ok then we'll have
the grand competition where all the
groups get up and you you choose one of
your members or two - to get up maybe -
and to present your items and then we'll
vote for the best ones okay so that's
the plan we stole it from China so far
we stole it from DCI we stole it from
the college okay
and we're going to do it better than
they do it okay cool any questions about
this process and you will get a notebook
every day and the notebook will have
some readings in it but not the main
meaning okay okay now when I taught ACI
the first time in New York for seven
years I made rules I had about I had
about seven students and I made a rule I
made a new rule you have to come to
every class sorry when I do a course it
has ten classes okay if you miss more
than two you cannot come back until the
next course that was my rule in New York
City and your ticket to the next class
is your homework if you don't have that
ticket you don't get into class third
thing I lock the door
at the start time I locked the door
and I remember a certain guy named MW
who bang on that he came one minute late
he's banging on the door he says you are
Dharma Hitler you know I'm like yeah
we'll come back next week and we were
yelling through the door at each other
you know and I said new new management
new management you know this is the new
system and I lost half of the students
in the first week it became for students
you know then I'm like maybe I'm just
you know maybe I made a mistake and then
it exploded it became like 80 students
in in one year it exploded but I can
really learn something you know I do
homework every time I do quiz every time
which is happening starting tomorrow in
the beginning of class well after the
meditation okay so you're gonna meditate
on your quiz no people learned a lot and
they loved it and more and more and more
and more people came we we gave up our
first classroom space we got rid of it
we got a new one we got rid of that we
got a third one we got rid of that we
got a fourth we had to keep expanding
and growing and going okay and then a
hundred people ended up coming to Dynamo
for the first advanced classes now in
the advanced classes I thought let me
relax a little bit I shouldn't be so
tough you know and I gave homeworks but
I did not require them and I had no
quizzes I think right Jing me no quizzes
and I trust people to come when they
that they will come to everything and
they didn't guess how many people
finished all the homeworks out of 138
people three
finish the homework okay then I decided
that's not such a good system okay so
what do I do with you guys
I have a new idea I don't think I can
force you to do everything but I have an
idea okay so every person this group is
is is limited to a hundred people how
many people here ten one hundred one
hundred and eight that's a good number
I will not expand it past a hundred and
eight okay and you have to earn a seat
here at the cantina so the people who
finish the most homeworks will get a
seat at the next ngons now okay and it's
got competition
so the 108 people who do the best who
finished the most okay and they will get
the best seats they will get the best
retreat cabin they get to choose their
cabin okay Tim's gonna make this all
work okay so you get your first choice
on your retreat cottage okay and you get
guaranteed seat in the class okay if you
comfort and I don't I'm not doing it by
Internet okay Buddhism is passed on by
human beings okay I'll do Internet if I
had to do internet but I don't like it
okay
I'm not an electric I'm a human being
you know and I prefer to teach in person
okay so once a year you can spend the
money you can get here okay once a year
get here for all the days and I will
prefer I will give the seats to the
people who come for the whole program
I'm not interested if you're interested
in two days or three days or five days
you know it's really just disruption for
the other people see it's a feeling you
get in the retreat
we're all silent and so that's my deal
okay I'm not going to kick you out
because we need you we need to sell all
the rooms but as it grows the people who
who finish their work and who come on
time and who come every day they will
get the best cottages and they will get
a guaranteed seed we taught at MIT they
have a program once a year called
gathering of Titans and there are 72
chairs in the room for 15 years and
there are 6,000 people waiting for a
chair there's a list of 6,000 people
waiting for a chair and and you get the
chair by coming and participating and
you know and though people fight for
those chairs and when we came into the
room to teach them we had to sign a
contract that we will not talk about
what goes on in that room so I can't
tell you that they are close to curing
pancreatic cancer and other things okay
amazing group of people okay so I kind
of like that okay so it's an honor to be
here you can make it once a year you
don't have to make it four times a year
it's not going to bankrupt you if your
husband want to divorce you bring him to
beautiful Bowie you know he can see all
those wonderful things there's an old
car there
[Music]
[Laughter]
I understand good okay that's my deal
for you okay and I want a hard core in
the guys in a group you know and I want
Khulna guards new people and you have to
be yourself you know this week I made
deals with people you can come five days
you can come forward and some people
coming from one day but that's the end
okay next starting next time I'm not
interested in any deal and the people
who came to the most classes this time
they will be treated they'll sit in the
front they will get special cappuccino
they will get their own choice of
retreat Kevin okay once a year okay
and I think I'll do some podcast to just
the guardian of podcast video so you
don't you know one year is a long time
so we'll try to do something in between
you know from my bathroom at my house
okay all right let's start the gardener
because I I kind of have to cover your
whole homework I will take another break
before the before and what time we
finish okay oh okay so I'll go for a
while on the gardener and then we'll
take a juice break okay first you have
to look so so good I say Luke's ah so
good eh
Adam you got that in your head I yeah
look so great means you have to make
room for the green thing you understand
pee pee and then we'll take a we'll take
a look so good right back and then what
we'll have Granger Grange a goal is to
make you smart okay not like coffee all
right so we're gonna study I in the
gardens you know I I don't even know how
to start
on IANA Gardiner you know I guess the
first thing I'd say is that I am eager
Gina is a I am and he's called the aya
sometimes it's just called the aria
Papa in Tibetan and I in Sanskrit and in
history he's he's the most famous aria
okay Aria means a person who saw
emptiness directly during meditation
deep meditation so if you want to be an
aria if you want to prepare someone to
become an aria you should do two things
you should teach them lion stance and
you should teach them the gardener guess
what we're doing this week yeah you're
doing both okay so in general I think I
can say that about every 500 years
one person is an aria okay about once
every 500 one person is an aria now if
you have a special group of people it's
possible all of them become arias okay
we can break this rule okay
the first teaching the Buddha ever gave
five people retire in the first teaching
that the Buddha every game so during
that first day five people became iron
so don't think it's impossible okay
you are unusual people you live in a
world where education is very very high
the number of people on the planet who
can read is about 80% that's the highest
it's been in history in history it's
never been that way so we live in
special times almost everybody has a has
a connection to the Internet
and we live in different times so I
believe we can increase the number of
artists okay so don't think it's
impossible it's been rare but we have
different tools now and we have
different education background so I
think it's possible I think it's
possible all of you can become iron and
that's what I want that's the goal of
this course I don't care that you know I
I in the garden his birthday or or the
sounds good name of his third book or
you know it's nice but what I really
want is this is a five year course on
how they become a are you okay and I'd
like you to teach it it's part of my
dream that you teach it we had no
limitations in the past on on teaching
and we're trying to put a few
limitations on it just in case
teachers have bad behavior or drinking
or or hurting people sexually or things
like that we are trying to to control a
little bit closer so I would say I want
all of you to teach new gardener I want
all of you to become and the gardener
teacher you can become unofficial
teacher you are not working for a CI we
call sharing in your living room okay so
you got to get a big living room alright
but sharing anyone can do okay teacher a
CI teacher we will have some
requirements we will have some
examinations we all have some training
ok so maybe I don't call you a CI
teacher maybe I call you in the guardian
a sharer okay but my dream is that you
share with other people the gardener and
with good behavior okay with good
personal behavior okay alright
so first of all he's an iron iron
literally means higher person okay
higher evolution I like to think of that
picture of the gorilla walking behind
the ape walking behind the caveman
walking behind the guy and if you're
higher evolution of people okay so
there's a there's a Turtles walk on the
from the ocean on to the beach then
they're slowly they learn to walk on two
legs then they become monkey then they
become caveman then they become human
and then you become Aria continue become
Buddha you say you have an evolution of
species and an aria is as different from
a normal human being as monkey is from a
turtle you see different completely
different kind of being so that name I
am means higher evolution and it's the
goal of human beings okay
we are not finished with our evolution
you know you were monkey million years
ago then you became a kind of
good-looking it he has
then you became this guy kind of not so
good-looking and then that you'll have
one more step to go we are not finished
okay a human evolution is not finished
and we still have one more step people
who understand the pan in DCI language
people understand that the world is
being created by seeds in their mind
okay and who lived according to that
understanding because if you understand
where things are coming from you can
have anything you want any kind of
happiness you can have you can have
financial independence you can have a
beautiful family life you can have a
different kind of health even an old age
you can be different if you understand
where things are coming from okay so
this is ayah so maybe the first Homer
question and the first quiz question
might be I'm not very good at keeping
secrets
that's what Veronica said don't tell
people that I said okay okay don't tell
him what I ate yesterday all right
what's the one event in his life that
defined area in the Gaggia and his
position in the Buddhist tradition he
saw emptiness directly okay he saw
emptiness directly that defined his
entire life and his entire teachings and
his teachings are so famous that he's
called the second Buddha to come to this
earth his nickname is Sangha younger
Jamba which means in in Buddhism they
call him Buddha number two second time
second time Buddha showed up on this
planet was iron a gardener okay and his
teachings about emptiness are the most
famous in this planet on
world okay his teachings about emptiness
are the foundation of all teachings on
emptiness in Buddhism okay his teachings
and his most famous teaching on
emptiness is called wisdom okay it's
just called wisdom Prats Nia
okay namah mood imagine markic Arika but
the short name is wisdom okay guess what
you're studying wisdom okay and I always
wanted to teach it for for twenty years
I wanted to teach him but I couldn't
find the right people now I've found the
right people okay
and I've been waiting for 20 years to
teach this okay all right
he also the gardener came about the the
Buddhist history say 400 years but
probably we now believe it's about 600
years after the Buddha
okay so there's about a 600 year 700
year gap okay I guess you could say 700
year gap after the Buddha came to Ghana
okay so what happened during those 700
years
Buddhism got really boring okay Buddhism
got really boring I'm sorry
it's Stanley's book called abhidharma
okay if you really can't sleep at night
Stanley's translation is available and
these guys these monks got all the
Buddhist teachings and they made a very
dry book called Abbey dimer okay I'll be
damned and so for seven hundred years
after the Buddha kind of the boring
people took over the kind of sitting in
a monastery and they have lots of rules
and the very dry dry books and I I
translated it for twelve years I studied
it for twelve years it was the first 12
years of my training was epidemic OSHA I
translated the whole thing I wrote a
dictionary for it I translated one of
the most famous commenters I spent 12
years on it and I loved it I respected
and it's boring and the emptiness
teaching is not they're not the same and
compassion teachings Bodhisattva
teachings are not there and they are
missing okay then the gardener came and
said we gotta put these two things back
these are sexy
you know emptiness and the Bodhisattvas
way of life we got to put these back
into the teachings so that's his he's
also famous for doing that he put us he
put the jalapeno back in the Buddhist
teachings okay
he brought the taste back to the
Buddhist teacher okay so he's famous for
that
okay he's famous for starting the
Mahayana starting the Mahayana the great
way a Buddhism where we have an ideal to
help the whole world I'm not just trying
to reach nirvana for myself I'm trying
to help the whole world become happy
okay and he sold that idea he started he
woke up that idea right of course the
Buddha taught that but these kind of
accountants took over after the burner
and
The Guardian that came back in he is
sexy he is fun he is cool he he is Miles
Davis Miles Davis famous jazz player and
he said less is more
he said did you know and he's like put
some spaces in your work you know make
it poetry don't drown people in words
like Geshe Michael does okay like and he
put poetry back in the birth teachings
and almost all his teachings are poetry
almost all his teachings are cara cara
cara cara cara comments written in
poetry written in poetry okay almost all
his major works I think I don't know 90%
he wrote in poetry and he wrote sweet
brief like mysterious poetry his Potter
is awesome
he also wrote a lot of Tantra he wrote a
lot on Tundra his teacher Sarah ha who I
think Sarek me is named after I don't
know probably his teacher was a great
great country teacher okay his first
teacher Sarah ha was a great tantric
teacher so a lot of the secret teachings
that we study especially something
called rim la the five stages of Tantra
these come from the gardener okay so he
was a great teacher of the higher of the
secret teachings diamond way diamond
wave Audrina okay and and the gardener
was the one who tied together the
Bodhisattva way of life to emptiness you
see he said you cannot be a bodhisattva
unless you understand emptiness you see
you it's not being nice to other people
or helping poor people it's not enough
you have to understand
those poor people are coming from you
okay
you must under you cannot love people
until you understand their coming from
you it's not possible to really love
people until you understand they are
coming from you
you must combine the two kinds of
bodhichitta we learned it at the college
for two weeks this month last month
anyway recently
what's the two kinds of bodhichitta
what's the two kinds of the wish for
enlightenment number one I myself will
become a Buddha to help all living
beings because a Buddha can serve all
living beings directly at the same time
okay as a dog as a tree as an ocean as
they're complaining mother-in-law okay
only a Buddha has this power okay I want
to be a Buddha so I can help all living
beings at the same time in any disguise
these guys as a movie star disguise as a
dog
this guy says Tim Lowe and how you know
okay I want to be a Buddha and like that
okay why so I can help them become a
Buddha okay that's body start our first
love of Bodhisattva bodhichitta the wish
to become a bodhisattva
what's the second kind what's the
ultimate mother to know the direct
emptiness of the dragon tennyson the
direct perception of emptiness okay the
direct perception the emptiness is
ultimate love okay it's name is ultimate
love okay you really love people you
really care about people you really want
to help people
then struggle during the gardens with
them okay struggle through his book
and it will help you see emptiness
directly only then can you really serve
people okay you cannot serve them before
none the service is not very good you
are like a three-star Hotel if you
didn't see emptiness directly okay
that makes you a five-star hotel okay
then your service is high-quality
okay got it okay so it's interesting
that the greatest master of emptiness in
history is also the person who brought
Bodhisattva way of life back to the
world is there connection that might
make a good real album
okay some connection there the one
person who could explain the best how
does the emptiness directly is also the
person who brought body stuff are ideal
back to Buddhism okay and if you're a
Christian if you grew up in a Christian
country there's some interesting
connections there taught the disciple
Thomas did go to doe job to northern
Afghanistan and did teach in Madras in
Chennai just before Nagarjuna and so
it's kind of and the gardener was
hanging out in those places so it's
interesting to dream of some connections
between the two I don't know okay second
home mmm
we're gonna use for principal sources
okay
I like principal sources I don't like to
just talk about my own idea I like to
take you to this incredibly niche as
John just found a hundred two hundred
thousand more books in Mongolia okay
Buddhist books and it's Christina here
comes the girl
yeah and John baby we should give them a
head yeah yeah they raised a million
dollars to save those books and it will
take 20 years but we have enough for the
first couple weeks right John just
kidding a couple years okay here's the
books we're going to use okay in in this
number one gasps wisdom okay we're going
to use the gardener book called wisdom
okay and I'm going to explain the longer
title I hope today so you can do your
homework but it's just called wisdom in
sense great present okay
it's called wisdom we're going to use
the Tibetan translation because the
Tibetans were like thematic translators
every single word is translated
perfectly I'd worked on the abhidhamma
culture for 12 years I found one extra
word in it they taste two words to
explain one word only once in the whole
thing okay they are amazing so we're
gonna use I know my training is in the
Tibetan I'll be working minded from the
Tibetan text
but luckily we have Christina we have
Aisha we have them mama
and they have found the Sanskrit and I'd
like to thank them yeah okay
so we'll be using the Sanskrit also on
so sometimes I'll take you to the
Sanskrit because English comes from
sounds good all Western languages from
Iceland to Iran come from Sanskrit so
sorry about Chinese there's some kind of
mistake
but you have a lot of loanwords from sin
screen from the tongue town
so we'll be studying in central by the
way the subtitle of wisdom okay
the small title under the big title is
root verses on the middle way root
verses on the middle way okay root
verses on the middle way okay now
there's a very famous commentary by some
kapa okay some copper wrote a commentary
it's called the ocean of emptiness I
translated as the ocean of emptiness
okay
and it's big it's huge
and it's deep and it's beautiful and it
would take us 20 years to do it and I'm
willing to but I am you know it didn't
the alarm it didn't seem to work out too
well so I there's another beautiful
commentary but moderate tsongkhapa
States you all know thirteen fifty seven
to fourteen nineteen if you want to get
into a if you need a password to guess a
password of someone in our group try
1357 okay
it's true I'm sorry I shouldn't put that
online right okay now that'll empty out
our accounts and find out there in
theory again so there was a lama who
came about two or three hundred years
after some after some couple named Tony
Lama Tony Lamas eh Oh anyway mama
recently I by mistake I didn't type to
see which makes honey Lama and I'm I've
just started calling him honey Lama but
I called Veronica honey Lama so but
anyway if you can't remember his name is
honey Lama with a see
okay Tony Lama his monks name is doc
bedroom dr a KP egg might be on your
homework
dr a second name said group sh e dr u p
he was born in 1675 he passed away in
1748 he wrote two hundred and fifty
unbelievable books and we are
translating many of them in in our
college and his explanations are
unbelievable his explanations are
beautiful and we can understand them so
i'm gonna use him mainly okay to teach
you wisdom he has a hundred page a 200
page commentary one hundred folios which
is about a thousand pages in the english
okay
it's an extraordinary commentary i can
translate it if you give me time okay if
I have time I can translate it quickly
but you gotta help me okay if I spend a
lot of time doing other things I cannot
okay so it's up to you
hmm I'm about to give you the name but
thank you for asking
guess what it's called a ship for
crossing what the ocean of emptiness
okay so he's making a joke
what's the joke it's yeah he's like he's
saying look so copies book is too hard
you need a boat don't go swimming out
there it's too far to China from
California you know don't go swimming
take my ship take my boat you know get
on my boat you have a chance to make it
over the ocean of emptiness if you don't
take my boat you're gonna drown
somewhere in some compass commentary
okay so I think it's a beautiful I just
noticed it like a week ago
oh my god he's talking about some copper
being hard you know you need to shipped
across from copper okay so that's three
books and then Tony Lama wrote a
condensate Connie Connie means the
author goes through a famous book and he
only what Adam yeah he only goes out to
the difficult points he just talks about
the nasty points that are difficult to
understand so Tony Lama well the second
commentary is shorter but it's nasty
it's hard okay
it's called difficult points in wisdom
okay difficult points in wisdom okay
those are the four that you need to put
on your homework and the next question
on your homework says there's another
very very famous explanation of Naga
Janus wisdom who wrote it what are his
dates and what's the name of his book
anybody
it's called entering the middle way okay
entering the middle way now
wisdom has a nickname okay wisdom has a
nickname
it's called middle way okay so middle
way you know we're gonna study what
middle way means okay but it's also a
nickname for the gardener's book
sometimes they call they don't call it
wisdom sometimes they call it the middle
way like people from Mexico City or New
York City who think they live in the
most important city in the world they
just saying the Mexico City people call
it Mexico you say where you're from
Mexico but what City Mexico then New
Yorkers you know I'm from the city you
know what the city I'm up City
okay right right you can get some coffee
from the New Yorkers anyway it's just
called a domino way when you say jump in
a way you're talking about with them
okay if you write an explanation of it
you can call it entering the middle way
entering middle way how to enter the
middle way and that verb in Tibetan and
Sun skin is the verb for crossing an
ocean also okay it's a pun okay so
entering the middle way which was
written around 650 650 ad by master
chandrakirti chandra CH a and DRA here
TK i RTI chandrakirti he wrote enter in
the middle way which became the most
famous explanation and emptiness ever
and all emptiness teachings
later come from there all teachings in
Tibet on emptiness thousands and
thousands of books come from
chandrakirti chandrakirti comes from the
gardener okay so so don't what is China
kidding me Chandra means moon moonlight
Gerty means famous and it means his
ideas are like moonlight they cover the
whole world you know if you guys do your
job and if you learn wisdom and if you
share it or teach it then this moonlight
will spread to the whole world
okay it's up to you you can be the next
chance it could be moonlight moonlight
give her something like that okay all
right I'm getting through the getting to
it so I'm gonna go through through with
you Tony Lamas commentary again if I get
time I can translate if I don't get time
I can it's up to you I'm working on
sixteen books right now in Tibetan I'm
working on about ten in English but if I
translate this extra one it's up to you
okay but the first thing in Tony Lamas
commentary okay here's one two three
verses he boughs down to his teachers
okay and this is every Buddhist book
starts with respect for the lineage in
your own teacher okay I can't teach you
if I didn't have my teacher you know I
would be a college professor somewhere
teaching I don't know what politics from
me okay I mean I cannot teach without my
teacher he cannot teach without his
teacher and it goes and you have a
direct lineage to turn to guilty okay
count you the Yamagata ready to galleon
239 wonderful girl to Nunavut officials
who wanted something I can count you the
lineages the de masters you have a
direct phone line to chandrakirti living
beings have passed it down you are in
the lineage now you are the next one in
the lineage okay you have direct lineage
has never been broken nobody taught it
very wrong in there sharing in their
living room for 1300 years and 2,000
years if you can regard for 2,000 years
it has been passed on without being
broken and you are some weird karma you
are sitting in the room where the next
generation is happening okay so how you
got here probably you're an amazing
person I know you don't want to believe
it but I'm sorry
you are amazing if you're sitting in
this room you are amazing okay so I
think it's significant that and if I
might even make a homework question
about it that the very first thing that
Tony Lamas says if you want to see
emptiness find someone who saw it or
find a person who can give you a clean
teaching about it you know an accurate
teaching about the instructions okay
find a teacher find a living teacher not
a electrons okay blood and bone and
coffee teeth okay like that real person
no I mean you know find a final a real
teaching because the blessing of these
things comes through from human to human
from person to person okay there's a
talking blessing you can get on the
internet there's a spiritual blessing
you have to be in the room
okay and those seats are gonna get
competitive I believe in a while which
means you have to finish your homework
which is your ticket to get your seat
all right one more and then I'll take it
back okay Tim don't get worried
no he's like get loud let's do story
time
okay let's do story time
so we're very lucky there it's hard to
find a good biography of Ngong Jeana I
want to tell you a little bit about his
life tomorrow I'm gonna tell you about
Tony Lamas life because I wrote a
biography recently it's about 20 pages
and I'd like to give you a biography of
Nagarjuna okay and this was written by
my Lama
I can remember Jay cash an awesome
person right and so he translated one of
the guards books in the English and he
wrote a nice introduction okay with my
good friend and jealousy object our
danghang who was his best student and I
did say it okay and I wrote him this
week I asked him can we can we use your
translate so he translated with my Lama
and he gave permission to print it for
you so it's gonna be in your notebook
you will have the history biography of
Nagaina I think it's the best one I've
ever seen but I'm gonna go through some
of it with you
okay so that you forget about the pee
pee break okay
and then we'll go to the rest of the
homework then we'll cover the rest of
homework okay yeah okay and I'm going to
mix in some of the oral teachings from
the monastery about nagamma okay he was
born in South India okay which is kind
of unusual
most of our masters come from North
India okay he was born in South India
which means he was more mellow people in
the South in their more mellow and
there's a place called the Vidarbha
which is land of the palm trees and in
our monastery which is in South India
there's a tradition when you go from the
airport which is Bangalore to our
monastery you pass through where the
governor was from and there's lots of
people selling coconuts so when you see
the coconut sellers on that drive that's
where the gardener is supposed to be
from okay
when he was born they his parents took
the child to a fortune-teller and he
said this baby is very very special but
he's gonna die in seven days the baby
will die in seven days and the parents
were like well what what can we do to
make it longer and they said well if you
make offerings to a hundred people of
food if you feed a hundred people he
will live for seven days and if you
offer to a hundred months food which I
guess the writer was among he will live
for seven years okay and he will die
after seven years there's nothing you
can do okay so of course the parents fed
the monks and the people and
then when seven years was coming they
decided to travel with the child
somewhere because they didn't want to be
there when the boy died they sent the
boy with some people on a trip and
coincidentally they walked to the
monastery of Nalanda which is the most
famous Buddhist monastery in history and
when they were there they met Saroja
okay Saroja was there this great teacher
great tantric are there are some
surviving tantric poems by Sir aha
a very famous songs of spiritual life
and so they told they told Sara her
about the boy's condition and they asked
him if there's anything he can do and he
said if you make the boy a monk it's
possible he will survive but he has to
do special mantras so he gave the boy
special mantras especially on the night
of his seventh birthday and he was doing
mantras to Amitabha and he survived he
defeated the Lord he faced the Lord of
death with amitabh us power and he
defeated the lord of death and so he had
a good start to his monk's life later on
Saroja taught him a lot and he had other
teachers in the monastery and eventually
he became important in the monastery
Nalanda monastery okay and I'll tell you
a personal story I used to be the
accountant for the monastery because I
was the only person who could use a
calculator so 2,000 months and
I'm the only person who can use at that
time I used to have contests with a guy
using an abacus and he would beat me a
lot something and so anyway I used to
complain to one of my teachers
geschichte intervention you know I said
I hate this accounting stuff you know
drives me crazy
I want to study I want to translate I
don't want to count you know how much
bags of flour the monastery used and you
know he said Oh big mistake you know I
said why he said who do you think was
the accountant in london' monastery I
said I don't know I don't care he said
it was no gardener the guys know with
the accountant I'm like no way he said
yeah it's true you know I said well why
would they put the best scholar in the
history to do the accounting you know
and he said the Karma of mishandling
dyma money is so serious that only
nagashi owner could handle the Karma
you see if you lose one penny ten cents
of Dharma money
terrible terrible karma very serious
karma so they decided to only in the
gardener can handle this Karma he said
the accountant in a monastery is the
most trusted and most amazing person in
the monastery only they can do it I'm
like yeah
[Laughter]
I take it check me anyway that's a
tradition okay and so he became the
accountant and then he decided I should
just learn how to make gold okay two out
we call alchemy in English how to make
gold from iron so he said if I could
learn that then all this accounting is
not really necessary you know I could
have more time to myself if I didn't
have to do fundraising all the time like
this week then he heard that there was a
someone on an island like a very strange
Island there was a magician who could
make gold out of iron so he decided to
go there like walk across the water but
you need a special kind of sandalwood
leaf you need a special tree need to to
do this walking across the water so he
kept one in his pocket
monk pocket and he kept one in his shoe
and he walked across the water and he
met the magician and he said will you
teach me how how to make gold okay
[Music]
I mean mmm is that I'm reading from this
yeah I want to read it to correctly okay
and so they started to exchange
knowledge the magician taught him how to
make gold but he stole the leaf out of
his pocket so he thought he cannot go
back and he will have to stay on the
island and he can't teach other people
how to make go but the gardener had one
in his shoe so he got back anyway
and he used his knowledge to support the
London monastery and there was a famine
for 12 years no money no food and he
supported all the monks using alchemy
okay now it's not in the biography but
there's a tradition that he was kicked
out of the monastery for some time
because it was not allowed to use
alchemy for a monk a monk not supposed
to keep money not supposed to have money
so it was not approved to to use this
magic but he did and the monastery
survived because of it but he was
disciplined and he was asked to lead the
monastery okay that's how oral tradition
he was actually kicked out of the master
so he I think he must have learned how
to handle disappointment or trouble you
know he saved the monastery and he was
kicked out of the monastery okay so
that's an oral tradition there's a
tradition that he kicked out the highest
total of monks ever kicked out when he
became the abbot
later he became he became the head of
Nalanda and he kicked out 8,000 months
for misbehavior they were not doing nice
behavior they were breaking the rules
probably with girls or alcohol or money
which is the big symbol three jewels and
he disciplined they say tradition says
he kicked down about 8,000 months he
took upon them then there was a problem
that are you okay
stories okay all right this is the easy
part and probably there's some ideas to
be mine in this story that's up to you
be creative so anyway there was some of
the books that the Buddha taught
Bordeaux below middle the perfection of
wisdom progeny a parameter were missing
in the world okay this is seven hundred
years after Buddha and some books are
missing so he was thinking how to get
them he had two students who came to his
class two young men when they were in
the class the whole room smells like
incense when they leave the incense
smell goes away so he decided this must
be water dragons in disguise Naga
ok Naga now that means dragon like in
England they have lots of dragons right
and you've got a finally can find some
was it st. Georges st. Michael no no
somebody's killing dragons anyway
there's a big tradition of dragons in
Europe there's a big tradition in China
in in in Buddhism they're called Nagas
and these are called water water dragons
they like ocean they like legs one of my
lamas says there's a Naga living up here
we have a spring here he says there's a
Naga living there you can't see them you
have to
special person to see them I have not
seen them I trust a llama by the way he
might come in the spring to teach
getting lotar so that would be a big
honor and they are just like in when
they call that movie Hobbit what's the
movie
Lord of the Rings yeah in the Lord of
the Rings Smaug smart Smaug the dragon
bad dragon that one thing about that
movie is true they like to collect
beautiful things okay
they're like Japanese book collectors
half the books in Mongolia disappeared
into the basement of Japanese book
collectors they can't read them but they
like them you see what I mean
dragons are just like done anything
bright like gold or jewels okay you can
see the movie I assign you to see the
movie what's it called Lord of the Rings
three movies right you have to so that's
a true story they like there are dragons
they like those things what's the most
valuable thing in this world is bottle
bola middle okay perfection of wisdom so
they used to take the books home into
their dragon homes and keep them and
usually they sit on valuable things so
it's hard to fight with them anyway
The Guardian has figured out that these
two young men are actually water dragons
in disguise and their father is called
tuk Shaka the most famous water dragon
of all time and he said do you guys have
any of these missing books back in your
dragon land you know that you are hiding
them and they said yeah we do you know
and
he negotiated he was tough he is all his
skills and he became the master of that
dragon okay
in ancient India master warrior is
called Arjuna Arjuna in the
bhagavad-gita the the hero's name the
biggest warrior is Archana okay it means
number one Chen Liang II Germany number
one either eat the general generally his
number one wolf warrior in the whole
world
Arjuna he's the boss he defeat the
dragon okay so his name is Naga Archana
okay in the gardener
we put the two words together the
gardener he the person who could control
the Dragons okay
and when on your notebook if you ever
get it I put a picture of him for you
usually they have snakes on the guard on
his head and they have a big hood and
they are shading his head because he was
also bald probably all wise people are
involved and they are protecting him
from the Sun like they used to take care
of him so sometimes the water dragon
will show as a Cobra and they will cover
in the gardener with their hood so you
can see eight or nine naga snakes in the
picture that's to show his in the
gardener so you can always identify in
the gardener easily in a painting he's
the guy with the snakes over his head
okay
alright let me see if there's anything
else to keep you from peepee
yeah they tried to get him to stay there
he said no I'm too busy he built a lot
of temples he built a lot of monasteries
he was a builder okay and he loved to
build statues he helped to restore the
Buddha tree Bodhi tree in vajrasana
nowadays is called bo gaya so he
protected that tree he built walls
around the tree he's famous for taking
care of the temple there he spent a lot
of money and a lot of time raising money
to build different kinds of temples and
and to take care of monks
he was a big organizer he loved to
organize things and he built a lot of
different monasteries the other thing oh
yeah I read in the Tang Dynasty records
of the western regions right this is a
swan song this famous Buddhist Chinese
who walked to India for 17 years he
wrote two famous well his most famous
book is you know became the novel
Journey to the West but he he was
required by the emperor of China to
write a economic and military assessment
of India and other kingdoms and it still
survives he counted his steps on the way
and based on his book we've found
travesty for example where the time
diamond cutter was thought based on
trend songs counting his steps in that
book we found 20 feet underground 6
meters underground they found travesti
City and I've been there where he
thought the diamond cutter that platform
is still there
so 20-some and this is just my own
edition okay he mentions that he went to
South India during his travels he also
went to Sri Lanka and he found Nicodemus
library and he said the first acip was
started by new gardener okay the
gardener was a really crazy about saving
ancient books collecting ancient books
preserving ancient books and he had the
first database Buddhism so I think it's
kind of cool that we're doing the same
thing here at our College okay last
thing I don't think there's anything
else missing
[Music]
yeah I'll tell you more about his book
yeah he was a good meditation teacher he
believed in meditation a lot there's a
funny story in his biography about his
student whose name was otto Singh ji
Tinky Tinky okay he had a student named
thinking and he was teaching meditation
for him this is a famous story he he as
a joke he told him to visualize that he
had horns on his head he said you know
go to the cave
the student was lying always bothering
when I met him why don't you I do I tell
you the life that yeah but what I do
okay go meditate on horns on your head
then he didn't come back and there was a
big thing at the monastery maybe think
he died in the cave and they sent these
monks to the cave and he's sitting there
very hungry and tired and what's the
problem I can't get out of the cave why
my horns are to be you know I can't get
to the door so he had maybe he was a
good meditation teacher okay nagamma
okay last thing they say some people say
he'd lived for seven hundred years
because he was an alchemist right he had
power over that some people say nine
hundred years but the story of how he
died is is still pretty famous there was
a king and a prince yeah and the prince
and his evil mother wanted him the boy
to be the new king but the old king
wouldn't die fast enough and the boy was
complaining and they went to ask
somebody what wisest king lived so long
he's living too long my son will never
be king they say
he has a connection to us to Nagarjuna
he has spiritual karma connection as
long as the Guardian is in life the king
will live if something happens to no
guardian of the king will die so they
did made a plan to kill the gardener and
they went to ask many people how to kill
the gardener and they said don't you
don't have to assassinate him you just
ask him
he's a buddy sama he will give you his
life you know just say I need your life
and he of course he will agree you know
so there boy and his mom when can you
will you die for us can we cut off your
hand he's like yeah okay go for it
and they took a sword and they they try
to cut his head but they wouldn't work
they couldn't cut his neck so they're
like upset
The Guardian like I'm sorry it's not my
fault it's your fault
and they said was there any way to kill
you and he said yes there is a way to
kill me and they said one and they said
many lifetimes ago I was a farmer and I
was cutting the harvest with a knife
with sickle and during the harvest I
killed the one button I cut one bug in
huh with the when I was cutting the
crops I cut one bug in huh so I have
this Karma
I still have this comma this scene so if
you try this kind of blade of grass one
piece of grass you can cut my head and
they say great and they ran and got to
see the grass and they cut off his head
and killed him
okay so he lived there's a lot of
confusion about his books there's a lot
of confusion about what he wrote partly
it's because he lived so long
partly after that people named their
kids in the gardener so there's a lot of
debate but that's the short story in the
gardener I have to say before I give you
a break in one minute
I haven't so far found a nice
explanation of how he saw emptiness okay
there's no Witsel cop bar we have a
record in his biography which in Jena
picked out yesterday he picked out the
first page we have the story in Talk '
but and I can check more today if I have
some time I'm not aware of that it's in
the history books when I've read about
you know what happened to him when he
saw him to miss directly okay all right
take a break 15 minutes come back I'll
finish your homework with you okay go
come back on time okay okay here we go
that's just your homework questions I
have to go faster I can't finish okay
that's a problem of this kind of system
all right all of the gardener's writings
are traditionally put into three groups
okay first one is called done that's all
I said to talk these are praises he
wrote songs of praise like love poems to
Buddha okay songs of praise then Tom Sox
a Tom so these are like discussions or
something like that
discourse ins teachings and the most
famous one there is called ratnavali
okay ratnavali which means the string of
jewels it's like
a rosary made of jewels okay that's very
very famous right now Valley
sometimes called Ratnam money mullah
okay and then there's his books called
books on reasoning okay like how to
figure something out okay books on
reasoning okay and for us these are the
most famous okay for us these are the
proofs for emptiness you can call them
books of proven proofs six books are
proofs okay six books are proofs in the
old days there was five then they moved
ratnavali into the proof for emptiness
his his one of his letters to a king was
moved from discussions to proof
so now we call Rick stop observing so
two six books of proof for emptiness
prove emptiness then I had a guy he came
to me recently he said we work out
things with our heart not with our head
you know we where we are working on her
heart not her head then I it bothered me
a little bit and I didn't say anything
but I went home and I said well we
figure out with our head how to work
with your heart you see like we do work
with our head a lot
in this tradition we do why because if
you use your eyes or your heart you may
not ever understand that things are
coming from you you need someone to
explain it to you you need someone to
explain it to you logically even people
who don't like logic they say I don't
like logic because and I say shut up
you're just used logic
you don't finish the body but you are
using magic right now when you say
because it's magic you see I mean people
try to prove to me why they don't like
watch it okay so we have a basic mistake
we are making about the world which was
built into our brain and our eyes and
our ears and our heart there's a mistake
in your equipment then you see
everything wrong everything and the only
way you can fix it is with because
somebody has to say because depend
there's a dog there's a human there's a
different way it must be coming from you
you need that okay it's called proof of
emptiness okay so his most famous books
is the third collection called books
that prove emptiness okay books on proof
okay I'm gonna give you 6 it's on your
homework might be on your quiz I hate it
when you study something 6 and what's
their specialty of each of the six and
then guess Allah doesn't put it on the
quiz it's not fair but that's your
problem okay so here's the six okay and
number one is wisdom okay the most
famous book he ever wrote it's the
longest one of the longest books he ever
wrote himself it's 32 pages in the
Tibetan okay a poetry and here's now on
your homework you have to say the name
of the book and you still have to say
the specialty of the book because each
of the six books has a specialty the
specialty of wisdom is to prove that the
objects of your perception color shapes
people building sky okay we're not
talking about the Antonis of you
that comes later we're talking about the
emptiness of the things around you is
the subject of wisdom okay that's the
main subject of wisdom the emptiness of
the things and the people that you see
around you is the main subject of wisdom
okay it doesn't mainly talk about the
state of mind the emptiness of your mind
it does not it's focusing on the things
around you okay now next book I like the
name it's called Smashing mistaken ideas
to dust like with a big hammer you know
smashing mistaken ideas to dust just
smash them okay this is guess what it
talks about specialty the emptiness of
the mind the empty set of the perceiver
okay the emptiness of the mind wisdom
focuses on the emptiness of things and
people outside and then smashing
mistaken ideas to dust focus on the
emptiness of your mind okay
the thoughts you hear in your mind are
also coming out of seats in your mind
the jenny is coming out of seeds in
Jenny's money okay Jenny and the
thoughts in Jenny's mind they're also
coming out of seeds okay
they are also empty they don't come from
their own side they are coming out of
how you treated people yesterday okay
got it all right and that book shows
that the state of mind which sees
emptiness is the key to Nirvana and
Buddhahood so the it demonstrates that
the subject state of mind which sees
emptiness is the key to become Buddha
okay and to reach nirvana okay what's
the difference between Nirvana and
Buddha
I'm nirvana I mean just easily yeah
nirvana you overcome your negativity
emotions cannot get angry cannot get
jealous
can I have desire okay then Buddhahood
you can have all people at the same time
much higher okay
Nirvana and Buddhahood the mind which
because which can see emptiness is the
subject of smashing things to dust okay
all right third one seventy verses on
emptiness seventy verses in the sanskrit
about emptiness okay it's called 70
poetry verses about the subject of
emptiness okay what's the specialty idea
there is that even though everything is
empty it still works 100% 100% okay it's
gasoline empty
yes does it make your car go yes okay
just because it's empty doesn't mean it
doesn't work okay things are empty but
you still have to be moral person you
still have to follow morality okay
emptiness doesn't free you from that it
forces you into them okay all right
number four is called defeating every
argument defeating every argument every
time someone gives you an argument you
defeat it okay that's a very interesting
subcategory of the last book okay number
four is kind of going deeper from number
three what was number three teaching
that things can work number four
teachers the logic can work logic
doesn't come from its own son thinking
doesn't come from its own son good
reasons don't come from their own son
but they were okay they're empty but
they work okay
good proofs for emptiness are empty us
but they were okay they can work okay
perfectly okay that's very cool right so
in a way book Forrest part is a sub book
of book 3 and book series a sub book a
book one all five of the other bugs come
from wisdom so you might put the word in
the subtitle of wisdom that these verses
are the moola these are the word persons
that in the title the subtitle of wisdom
is what root verses on the middle way
root verses on the middle way okay mula
sa Pragya sarracenia nama mula madhyama
car car car
okay the word mullah root foundation is
in the title of wisdom okay root versus
Y because it's the root of the other
five books okay and it's the root of
every book on emptiness since then okay
can we call it moola can we call it root
duh okay why every book on emptiness
comes from this book okay it is the room
okay so the nickname one of the
subtitles is say mullah Maha Makar
gotta calm okay root verses on the
middle way okay all right number five
sixty verses unreasoning I was hoping
Nick would be here because he's
translating it and the impossible
commentary tonight but in this book The
Guardian that discusses the two extremes
okay the two extremes ready number one
if things sorry
nothing number one things exist the way
they look like things exist the way they
seem to be it looks like one guy is
coming from one shop from here from here
over here it looks like one shots over
there and one shots coming towards me it
looks like that but it's not true okay
so that's called things exist do do
things don't exist the way you thought
okay they don't exist
the way they seem okay then somebody got
extreme reaction they said if things are
not the way they seem then they don't
exist at all I can do whatever I want
there's no Karma there's no morality
everything is Tundra okay
now someone's going to take that out and
put it on the Internet alright got it
that's a to extreme extreme number one
everything exists the way it seems to be
extreme number two if it doesn't then it
doesn't exist at all okay
these are two big run ideas now question
for you if the homework questions say
what's the word maha maka in the tire
you're gonna say middle-way okay
everything exists the way it looks like
over here if it doesn't exist the way it
looks like it doesn't exist at all over
here and where's my head my shining head
in the middle in the business okay okay
that's meaning a middle way okay don't
go this way don't go this way what's
this way everything exists the way it
seems to be long shot sitting over there
I'm over here she's coming at me and
that's exists oh but she doesn't exist
our guest okay then she doesn't exist at
all it's all illusion one shots not
there you know I don't have to send that
matter I promised to send for her two
months ago you know she don't exist at
all okay these are too extreme and
middle way means midnight now book
number five called 6060 vs. unreasoning
okay that one talked about those two
extremes okay that one talks about those
two extremes and it says if you
understand those two extremes you can
reach nirvana you can reach nirvana okay
what did I not include just now yeah I
didn't say Buddhahood book number five
main subject avoid the two extremes use
the middle way reach nirvana but he
didn't talk about Bodhisattvas he didn't
talk about Buddhist it's almost as if he
designed that book for those abhidhamma
accountant people and it's true okay
book number five was written for those
people this boring you know people don't
talk about Bodhisattvas they don't talk
about enlightenment they don't talk
about saving all living be
they just want a recent nirvana they go
to a cave they try not to do anything
and they reach nirvana
okay so book number five was mainly
meant for lower way people like
abhidharma time people okay and by the
way he doesn't mention it here but Nick
can tell you for book number five he
uses the lower way sutras to prove that
Buddha talked about emptiness to the
abhidhamma people but they forgot to him
put it in the book they didn't
understand it okay the accountants
forgot to put emptiness in the book okay
that's part of book five the gardener is
showing them and the gardener does a
very cute thing he doesn't use any
higher wave sutras input number five he
uses their own books to prove they're
wrong okay he uses the abhidharma
accountant guys books to prove the
accountant avatar my guys are wrong okay
got it okay
book number six which was kind of stolen
from the collection of discourse miss
Duncan so it's called the string of
precious jewels okay Ratna mala or
ratnavali okay gladness bow bow Oh jewel
and string of it means Rosalie okay of
jewels and that's his longest book
except for the one we're studying
they're about the same length okay and
many many llamas in the world like to
teach this one this one you can hear
very often it's very very beautiful it's
very powerful I think during lamb rim
desert periods in Thailand
or Mexico we will use that okay we'll
use it's very sexy it's very beautiful
it's different it's a different
presentation okay
why it focuses on explaining why if you
stick to the middle way if you avoid the
two extremes you can also reach for
Buddhahood for Buddhahood so what's the
difference between on your homework
between book number five and book number
six book number five focus on using
middle way to reach personal nirvana
personal mike-mike reach nirvana
okay book number six focus on reaching
the same middle way same two extremes
how to reach for Buddhahood okay now you
understand his sixth grade books on
emptiness okay and it's really something
you should remember probably there's
about three or four things there you can
use in your life okay that's up to you
okay probably there's some kind of flow
between the six books I didn't I feel
it's there but I didn't figure it out
probably there's some kind of cool flow
okay Tim I might go a little bit over
they told me their butts don't feel bad
yet and they they want me to go a little
longer maybe homework six questions give
the title of our book in Sanskrit
language okay yeah and tell me some
English words that come from those words
which are called cognate okay cognate
means an English word that comes from
the Sanskrit word so you can appreciate
the Sanskrit tunnel more if you
understand some English words that come
from the Sanskrit tunnel okay
all all English 90% of English comes
from Sanskrit if you know Sanskrit well
and you pick up a newspaper you can see
all the Sanskrit laying under the
Paige it's very cool okay here we go
first word is Virginia separate senior
okay Platts no price Nia means wisdom
okay
proud means number-one best most good
okay bra means very good super good okay
it comes in the English word proud I'm
number one proper proud I'm number one
prow of a boat I'm the front of the boat
the front of the boat is called prowl
okay the word for word comes from prop
it means up ahead in the front okay so P
becomes F in English okay sounds good P
becomes a front from okay forward okay
yeah means to know and in English we
have this word know okay
why they put those of you who you know
the English spelling is crazy
okay and Oh dumb you okay KN w guess not
why is the K there we don't pronounce it
right we don't take Kunal it comes from
here it comes from the J okay so no
comes from Sania
so what is pres yummy that's knowing
that's knowing wisdom with them best
knowing okay the word recognized comes
from done the word ignorance comes from
done okay alright okay the next word in
the title is the word word but words not
here to learn me say nom
namah namah means name okay
nama means name okay that's easy I don't
have to explain that nominate comes from
that nominal name okay
very few people called the goddess bunk
by a single word
very few people call it wisdom they will
call it
foundational verses on the perfection of
with or something like that they will
give it a long name okay who wouldn't do
that my gosh okay understand he likes he
says like Miles Davis less is more
he never didn't write in poetry he never
didn't write in short words he loves
sexy short names like you are going to
give to your real applications okay
he loves short names okay so call it
wisdom in this room call it wisdom when
you get outside you can say foundational
verses explain in the middle way of the
perfection of wisdom and he may have
knowledge okay if you want to write a
book that no one will read okay it won't
last for 2,000 years
give it a long name okay okay so press
me on nama means I call my book wisdom
that's all okay it's like a quotation
mark with them okay then there's a
little explanation subtitles submit
ready
Mulla Mulla it means cow just kidding
Mulla means rude moolah means foundation
okay in English we say money is the root
of all evil and we call money moola
sometimes so you can remember okay
mullah means root there's a very few
there's a Latin words for the wall like
more day which means mural means written
on the wall so ammunition comes from
that it means a fortified wall
it means foundation okay so mullah mean
we know mooladhara chakra in yoga
i'm sure what that's gonna stimulate
your mother dark chocolate today i'm
gonna do yoga so if you want to be cool
you can hang out in here and do yoga
just today Maha Maha Maha maka
okay makamaka middle way okay Matt yeah
and it came into English as medium or
moderate or middle middle culture Madea
Madea
okay Maha keep middle way don't go to
this too extreme
okay everything is looks is the way it
looks like or if it's not then it
doesn't exist stay in the middle way
madam okay middle way
okay last word of the title say Kartika
Kartika means it's important is written
in poetry okay
karna Chi comes from the word curve
which means to create or to make karma
comes from the create comes from done
cereal comes from that in English the K
DK mercy Crescent comes from done okay
it all means to do something what to
make something what to make it into cute
little verses that people can remember
for 2,000 years
okay alright last question now I'm not
even gonna tell you you're gonna have to
figure out that one
okay Tim I made it nine minutes over you
have some announcements or anything and
I'll go to the commentary tomorrow okay
we'll start to the commentary I had to
explain the rules for you to be who's
feeling like doing him and honey it's
all about you
[Music]
so Tashi shhh our show